<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some observations on the remarks upon the Quakers, or, The busie priest's envy detected and folly manifested and his poor ability for his languishing-church proved ineffectual.</title>
            <author>Field, John, 1652-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41277</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11209624</idno>
  <idno type="VID">46804</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248496608</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29828</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11209624</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41277)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46804)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1441:68)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some observations on the remarks upon the Quakers, or, The busie priest's envy detected and folly manifested and his poor ability for his languishing-church proved ineffectual.</title>
                  <author>Field, John, 1652-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing, NUC pre-1956 imprints to John Field.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: by one that is called a Quaker.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Relations --  Society of Friends.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Relations --  Catholic Church.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46804:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46804:1"/>
            <p>SOME OBSERVATIONS ON THE REMARKS UPON THE QUAKERS: OR, THE <hi>Busie Priest's</hi> ENVY Detected, AND FOLLY Manifested; And his poor Ability for his <hi>Languishing-Churh</hi> Proved Ineffectual.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 21. 10.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Soul of the Wicked desireth Evil: His Neighbour findeth no Favour in his Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Psal. 84. 14.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord will not cast of his People, neither will he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake his Inheritance.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle,</hi> in <hi>White-Hart-Court,</hi> in <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious-Street,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:46804:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46804:2"/>
            <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>ALtho' the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> in their great Wisdom, with Regard to the good of the Nation, and for Uniting of the Hearts of the King's Protestant Subjects in <hi>Interest</hi> and <hi>Affection,</hi> have seen meet to grant Indulgence to Tender Consciences, in the Exercise of Religious Worship; yet there needs but little Observation to inform, to what a height of <hi>Rancor</hi> and <hi>Prejudice</hi> some <hi>Parsons</hi> (and such as they can Influence) are grown, whose particular Interest, and earnest Desire (to gratifie their Wills, and to be at their old Trade of Persecution) is such, that they would frustrate the designed Good to the Nation, and break the good Unity in <hi>Interest and Affection,</hi> of the King's <hi>Protestant Subjects;</hi> knowing they shall thereby weaken the Interest of the <hi>Protestants,</hi> if they can divide them, and provoke them to fall one upon another; remembring that saying, <hi>That a Kingdom divided against it self, cannot stand:</hi> And those that are most hot at this Work, give cause to suspect, they are such <hi>Tools</hi> and <hi>Emissaries</hi> that are imployed by a contrary Interest to the <hi>Protestants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And their Cry of <hi>Heresie, Hereticks, Wolves, Cloven-foot Saints,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Denyers of the Trinity,</hi> doth savour of their persecuting Spirit: And their charging those that the Parliament have Recognized <hi>Protestant Dissenters,</hi> with the opprobrious Names of <hi>Blasphemers, Impostors, Cheats, Knaves, Renouncers of Christianity, and with laying aside the Lord Jesus Christ, and being Despisers of the Scriptures, Inconsistent with State, Inclinable to Disturb the Peace,</hi> shews the small Reverence they have to their Governours, to Insinuate, that they were so Unwise and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, as to Indulge such, and Recognize <hi>them</hi> for Protestants, that are Blasphemers, and Denyers of Christ, as they falsly say.</p>
            <p>And this shews not only their small Reverence to their <hi>Governours,</hi> but their great <hi>Design</hi> to <hi>Alienate</hi> and <hi>Divide</hi> the Affections of the King's <hi>Protestant Subjects;</hi> and tends to <hi>Incense</hi> them one against another, that now God in Mercy, and by his Providence, affords us <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Plenty</hi> in our Native Land, we might not enjoy that Blessing, by quietly living according to that Religion, which is an
<pb facs="tcp:46804:3"/> Institution of Love; and the Tenor of which is, <hi>Glory to God in the highest, Peace on Earth, and good Will to all Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, it seems to me, this, and such other prejudiced Priests, with such of their angry Hearers as they can prevail with, and Influence, would have the Protestant Dissenters, in this time of Peace, <hi>Suppressed,</hi> and not <hi>Tolerated</hi> nor <hi>Indulged,</hi> to give Glory to God in the highest, in their <hi>Peaceable, Religious</hi> and <hi>Christian Assemblies;</hi> nor suffered to live Quietly and Peaceably on the Earth, and in the <hi>Nation</hi> wherein they were Born, altho' he, or such as he, live at Ease, and enjoy plenty from the Sweat of other Mens Brows, and the Labours of those he is so angry with: Oh! what Shame it is that any of his Pretensions should be found in such Work! Will nothing serve him, but to have those that live in Love and Peace disturbed, that he so severely charges them to be <hi>Blasphemers,</hi> and so <hi>vehemently</hi> cries out against them, whose constant care hath been, under all the various <hi>Governments,</hi> since they were a People, to live <hi>Peaceably</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offensively?</hi> What aileth this angry <hi>Priest?</hi> Doth he want to have Ill-minded Men (like himself) again encouraged, such that have in days past been too much countenanced, (to Inform and give false Witness against this <hi>Honest, Industrious</hi> and <hi>Laborious People;)</hi> whereby many have been great Sufferers in Body and Estate, by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their <hi>Blood</hi> spilt in the <hi>Streets,</hi> and great <hi>Havock</hi> made upon their <hi>Goods,</hi> by <hi>Lewd, Loose, Idle Persons,</hi> of <hi>ill Fame,</hi> that were either never so Industrious and Diligent to get Estates, or otherwise by their Loose, Ungodly and Extravagant Living, to spend what their <hi>Parents</hi> got. If he would not encourage such, what means his calling to have the Quakers <hi>Suppressed,</hi> and <hi>Coertion</hi> exercised; and his say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I do not think the Ring-leaders among them worthy of so much Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion?</hi> Is it not then reasonable to conclude, <hi>that his tender Mercies would be Cruelty?</hi> And indeed (this was the old way of those whose Works declared they were not what they would be accounted;) their Speech bewrays, and their Writings declares them to be of a bitter <hi>persecuting</hi> Spirit, by crying out, <hi>The best way we can take against the Quakers, is to Address the King, and to Petition our Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives in Parliament;</hi> adding, as this Priest doth, <hi>I can't see what Law will oppose our Wishes, the Quakers having been favoured too long; let us not be Fools any longer, but call upon one another for Assistance against the Quakers; and Men of all Perswasions, Combine and Confederate against them.</hi> It seems he wants those that are Dissenters from his <hi>Languishing Church,</hi> as he calls it, to joyn with her against the Quakers. Oh! what an out-cry is here? Surely I may say, as <hi>Marien</hi> Bishop of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:46804:3"/> in <hi>Bithynia,</hi> did to <hi>Julian</hi> the Apostate, <hi>viz. In mine Opinion, he is a Persecutor which molesteth any kind of way, such Men that lead a quiet and peaceable Life. Julian</hi> in this sort afflicted the Christians not a little; so this Priest may see whose Example he follows, and would have others to follow, if they have no more <hi>Wit</hi> or <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity</hi> than he: But I hope, and am perswaded, we have now such a <hi>King,</hi> that will not follow that <hi>Emperors</hi> Example, however he may be excited thereto (by such busie and envious <hi>Priests)</hi> neither will, it's hoped, his great <hi>Council,</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> any more <hi>Countenance</hi> such <hi>Petitions</hi> hereafter, then they did the last Sessions, those from <hi>Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Norfolk,</hi> where the Priests had prevailed with some to Petition to have the Quakers Suppressed: See the Answer to them Petitions, where that Spirit, and its evil Designs, are opened, and set forth in their proper Colours.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:46804:4"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of some of this Priests notorious Lyes.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Introd. Chap.</hi> 5.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers want Patience in themselves, and Permission from their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors to Read the Books that are writ against them.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 7.</cell>
                     <cell>—None comes nearer the Papists than the Quakers.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 8.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers Disown, both in their Writings and Preaching, the Divinity of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers declare it utterly Impracticable, to deprive them of the present Benefits of passing their Words.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers Trade with none but themselves.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 10.</cell>
                     <cell>They seldom or never give a Farthing to any of a Different Perswasion.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 13.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers set their own Authorities above the Scriptures.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 15.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers set up for Infallible Persons.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers, in our Controversies with them, will not be judged by the Holy Scriptures.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 16.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>It is never usual for the Quakers to ask God Pardon for what they have done, tho' there is need enough of it.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers quite lay aside our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, thinking to be saved without him.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers deny and destroy the ever Blessed Trinity.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers have preached down all outward Devotion and Decency in Religion.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 17.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers Curse and Damn all the World besides themselves.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 18.</cell>
                     <cell>I have not misrepresented the Quakers in the least here, for nothing hath been charged to their Score, but is naturally deducible from the great Principle of the Light within.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 26.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers have Renounced Christianity at the bottom.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 28.</cell>
                     <cell>The Quakers have owned, that Priests of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have often preached amongst them.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To these I might add more, but think these too many,</hi> viz. <hi>as his lying ridiculous Stories, in p.</hi> 21. <hi>about the Quakers, and a Schollar's Speaking in the Quakers Meeting, who the Quakers called</hi> Daniel, <hi>and magnified God for him, when it was a Cheat under Disguise.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46804:4"/>
            <head>SOME OBSERVATIONS ON THE REMARKS Upon the Quakers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Remarks,</hi> Chap. 1. Page 1. <q>WHo but the Quakers, amongst their Neighbours, for godly Men and upright Dealers? And what confirms it, is a constant Care to abstain from vain Oaths and idle Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions—a great plainness in their Discourse, and a plausible pretence of standing inviolably to their Word; they appear withal, Meek and Lowly in their own, and in the Eyes of others; so far from Pride, and the Flattery of the World, that they never give nor take the common Civilities of the Age or Country.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And that Men may judge of their Intentions by their Outside, the <hi>Quakers</hi> Dress is Mean and Humble, such as becomes the Pure in Heart, which is justly <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Note,</hi> If their Dress be commendable, is not the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Dresses of many others, their high Heads, and patch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Faces, condemnable? Why then are not the former imitated, and the latter for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken?</note> commendable, we ought to acknowledge, and respect where ever we find it, and so we do in them.—The Quakers speak but seldom, and then it comes from them like an Oracle;—and are upright enough in their Intentions.—Thus the <hi>Quakers</hi> recommend themselves to the common People</q> [and are willing so to recommend themselves to all People] <q>and gain their good Opinion, or at least their Notice.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Observation.</hi> These are granted to be the Ways and Means by which the <hi>Quakers</hi> set themselves off to the best advantage, and gain the good Opinion of the common People; and what ever <hi>Offence</hi> it may be to this Priest,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46804:5"/> we esteem it both <hi>Christian,</hi> and <hi>Agreeable</hi> to the <hi>King's</hi> Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for Preventing and Punishing <hi>Immorality</hi> and <hi>Prophaness;</hi> and the late Queen's Gracious Letter, and for the suppressing <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaness</hi> and <hi>Debauchery;</hi> and the Humble Address of the <hi>House of Commons,</hi> for the suppressing <hi>Prophaness</hi> and <hi>Vice;</hi> and what he doth contrary thereto; and to what is said in that Book, so highly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended by a great number of Lords, Bishops, and most of the Judges of the Land, intituled, <hi>An Account of the Societies for Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Manners,</hi> &amp;c. Were what is Advised to therein, practised, he would not have writ as he hath, <q>And now especially the times of Peace are returned, which we have been told, are the times of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</q> as in p. 20. of the said Book, then should not this busie Priest have been so earnest to blow up <hi>Persecution;</hi> and by what skill he hath endeavoured to raise that <hi>Monster</hi> again, that hath been so long laid; read what followeth, p. 27. <q>Let all our Learned <hi>Rabbies,</hi> the great <hi>Disputers</hi> of the World, and all that make Profession of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> but give little better Account of it, than by expressing a <hi>fierce</hi> and <hi>uncharitable Heat,</hi> against those that differ from them, in some things relating to <hi>Religion,</hi> but not essential to it,</q> [by calling them, they give the Character afore-quoted unto, <hi>Blasphemers, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Cheats, Impostors,</hi> &amp;c.] <q>and wherein all Men, equally Wise and Good, have, I doubt not, never yet been fully agreed; think seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously with themselves, whether they may not better Imploy some share, at least of their Parts and Zeal, to much better purpose, in furthering the <hi>Reformation</hi> of Mens <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Manners</hi> of the Nation, by suppressing <hi>Prophaness</hi> and <hi>Vice,</hi> than by raising or keeping up with an <hi>Unchristian</hi> Temper [as this Priest doth] to the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest Injury of the <hi>Christian Religion,</hi> which is an <hi>Institution of Love,</hi> dangerous or unnecessary <hi>Controversies</hi> or <hi>Divisions.</hi>
               </q> Neither would he, if he had followed this Advice, have called for suppressing the Quakers, for Professing and Practicing that Religion which is an Institution of Love, and living Peaceably under the Government, which he tacitely Reflects upon for the <hi>Indulgence</hi> they have <hi>granted,</hi> and we <hi>gratefully acknowledge;</hi> neither is this agreeable to the Advice aforesaid, nor becoming any, much less a professed Minister of Christ, that <hi>came not to Destroy Men's Lives, but to Save them,</hi> to be so earnest and industrious for Persecution as he is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rem.</hi> Chap. 2. p. 3. This Priest also tells a strange thing, and delivers it in manner following, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>They <hi>(i. e.</hi> Quakers) prevail with some, and make them Converts before he is aware;</q> which may be his Grief, who saith, <hi>To his satisfaction he hath endeavoured accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46804:5"/> to his poor Ability, to prevent the Mischief that's threatned to the best of Churches</hi> (altho' Languishing, as he confesses) p. 29, 30.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rem.</hi> Chap. 3. p. 3. Again this Priest (as he owns he is) saith, <q>'tis not a Fiction of my own, but plain matter of Fact, that many have been enticed, and hired with Money, into the Party, and the event hath confirmed it beyond denial.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obser.</hi> We have this Parsons Word, that this is no Fiction of his, but plain matter of Fact, but he offers no proof, and I challenge him, and those of his Fraternity that are like minded with him, and will take his Word, to prove it: But if they account his Word may be taken, then their <hi>Church</hi> is <hi>Languishing,</hi> and may not I truly say, They give cause to think so, when they so liberally part with their Money to <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> for his Books and his Services; and what Hire or Reward <hi>G. K.</hi> hath from them, (since he is become a Sworn Deacon among them,) is best known to him he Swore by and to, and those in whose Pulpits he Preaches: And would ever such Tools be made use of by the Bishops of <hi>London, Norwich</hi> and <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln,</hi> &amp;c. and sent about City and Country, if they were not under some Apprehensions of the <hi>Languishing</hi> Condition of their <hi>Church,</hi> as this Son of hers says.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rem.</hi> Chap. 4. p. 4. He seigns a Story of a Quakers Visiting one that is not a Quaker, and calls it the Method of Converting; which Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Story, after he hath confidently told, he as falsly affirms, <q>They do so where ever they come; and says positively, This is the way, and nothing but matter of Fact; and I am confident (says he) that most Persons that have any knowledge of the Quakers—must needs own, that they have found them thus going to Work, <hi>viz.</hi> He, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Quaker, contrives some way or other to make a Visit—the Quaker sits for some time—but at last he takes an opportunity to open his Mouth, and (as he feigns him) saith, <hi>Friend, at my first coming under thy Roof, I did not know that I had any thing to say to thee; but since my coming here, I have received a Word from the Lord—</hi>And thus saith the Lord, <hi>Come out of Darkness, and be enlightned, that thou may'st be saved, and all thy House.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obser.</hi> Now he asserts they do so where-ever they come, which is notoriously false; and that this proves them greater <hi>Knaves</hi> than <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> saith he. I shall leave it to all to whom Quakers come, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether this be nothing but matter of Fact, as related, or nothing but <hi>Fiction</hi> in this <hi>Parson;</hi> and whether this Man is not more ridiculous herein than he renders the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rem.</hi> Chap. 5. p. 5. He pretends to tell the Arguments made use
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46804:6"/> of to Alienate the People from their own, and bring them over to the Perswasion of the Quakers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1st,</hi>
               <q>When a thing is Odd or Mystical, it is sure to be more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected for its being so.—The Quakers are very sensible of this, and therefore are purposely provided with uncommon Expressions, dark Words—such as <hi>spiritual Worship, spiritual Worshippers,</hi> and the <hi>Light within,</hi> with which they amuse the common People.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obser.</hi> What blindness and Ignorance this Man appears in, to call the Expressions of <hi>spiritual Worship,</hi> and <hi>spiritual Worshippers,</hi> and the <hi>Light within,</hi> dark Words? Surely he is very Dark and Ignorant of the <hi>spiritual Worship</hi> Christ spoke of; and is not such a Worshipper that Christ said, <hi>the Father seeketh to Worship him,</hi> for they Worship in the <hi>Spirit and Truth,</hi> which this Man Ridicules and Rejects; and thereby shews he is not Taught by Christ, and therefore unfit to be a Preacher of him to others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> He complains, <q>That the Quakers abate the good Opinion the common People have of their Parish-Ministers, and in order to it, tells them, That he is an Hireling—who does nothing but for filthy Lucre, Preaching for Tythe Piggs, Geese and Capons—A Doctrine one may be sure (say this Priest) is very agreeable with many amongst the Vulgar, who pay their Tythes with a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing Mind, and grudge the Minister should have One in Ten.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obser.</hi> How can the Quakers abate the good Opinion of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, when they have not so good Opinion of them, as to pay their <hi>Tythes</hi> willingly; but some for Fear may, least if they should with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a <hi>Tythe Goose</hi> or <hi>Pigg,</hi> or a few <hi>Eggs</hi> or <hi>Plumbs,</hi> they should be <hi>Subpoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na'd</hi> to the <hi>Exchequer</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> altho they live 200 Miles from it; and then have a <hi>Non est Inventus</hi> returned, altho' they are easily to be found, they not absconding, and yet have an Attachment for non-Appearance taken against them; or if they do appear, are committed to Goal, and Run to a Sequestration against their Estates, for a Contempt; and so by such Angry Parish-Priests, who to shew their Revenge against them that are unwilling to pay them, as some for Conscience sake are, then get their Goods and Estates siezed, and thereby put them to Forty, Sixty, or One Hundred times more loss, than what is pretended to be due for Tythes; and tho' the Priest get little by it, yet will they take these severe ways, although by Act of Parliament there is provided a more easie way for them to Recover their <hi>Tythes;</hi> but that doth not so well please many of the <hi>Angry Envious</hi> and <hi>Revengeful Parish-Priests,</hi> like unto Ruining of <hi>Families,</hi> Parting <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Wife,</hi> endangering thereby the poor Country-man's <hi>Life,</hi> by depriving him of Breathing in his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46804:6"/>
               <hi>Native Air,</hi> and shutting him up in a close nasty <hi>Goal,</hi> above 100 <hi>Miles</hi> many times from his <hi>Family</hi> (as there are many Instances) whereby his <hi>Wife</hi> is sometimes made a <hi>Widow,</hi> and his <hi>Children Fatherless;</hi> and if there be ten of them <hi>Children,</hi> the Priest will not have one of them, but either the <hi>Parish,</hi> their <hi>Friends,</hi> or <hi>Relations,</hi> must <hi>provide</hi> for them, when the poor <hi>Father</hi> is <hi>Dead,</hi> and the <hi>Family Ruined,</hi> or they may <hi>Starve</hi> for him; and this is the way that many of them take. But whether these things render them <hi>Ministers of Christ, Hirelings,</hi> or such that seek the <hi>Fleece</hi> more than the <hi>Flock,</hi> or demonstrates them to be in the <hi>Spirit, Practice</hi> or <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> let true <hi>Christians</hi> Judge; for by their <hi>Fruits</hi> they are known, whatever <hi>Cloathing</hi> they have, or however broad their <hi>Philacteries</hi> are, and how well so ever they love <hi>Greeting</hi> in the <hi>Market-place,</hi> and to be called of Men <hi>Master,</hi> it may easily appear whose <hi>Servants</hi> they are.</p>
            <p>But this Priest says in the same Page, <q>God never designed his <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters</hi> should Serve for <hi>nothing.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obser.</hi> He pretends here to be positively acquainted with <hi>God's Designs;</hi> but his own <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Design</hi> is <hi>manifest,</hi> that he is not willing to <hi>Serve</hi> for <hi>nothing,</hi> or to stand to the <hi>Discretion</hi> or <hi>Benevolence</hi> of the <hi>People;</hi> for indeed were he and his <hi>Brethren</hi> left to their <hi>Discretion</hi> and <hi>Benevolence,</hi> they would not have so many <hi>Thousands</hi> and <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds per</hi> Year, as some of them have; for they pay their <hi>Tythes</hi> with a very unwilling Mind, as he confesseth, which <hi>shews</hi> they are sensible their <hi>Preaching</hi> hath but little effect upon the <hi>People;</hi> and the <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> of many of them are such, that no ways <hi>Recommends</hi> them to be what they would be accounted; and therefore <hi>Coertion, Force</hi> and <hi>Violence,</hi> are their knocking <hi>Arguments</hi> to them that do not receive them, and pay them.</p>
            <p>Again saith this Priest, p. 6. <q>There is less reason still for Men to <hi>grudge</hi> the <hi>Tythes</hi> to their <hi>Ministers,</hi> or think they pay them in their own <hi>Wrong,</hi> since the <hi>Tythe</hi> is what the <hi>Laity</hi> never had a Title to; for if the Increase be God's, then nothing is more certain, than that the Tenth was never theirs,</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obser.</hi> He here excludes all his, or others <hi>Hearers</hi> from being God's <hi>Heritage,</hi> and thereby from a <hi>Right</hi> to <hi>Tythes;</hi> and if they are not God's <hi>Heritage,</hi> What hath his and their <hi>Preaching</hi> benefited them? If he and they say, They are the <hi>Heritage</hi> of God (as <hi>Clergy</hi> signifies) then they have a Right to their own <hi>Tythes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, If <hi>Tythes</hi> be the Increase, and the Increase God's, then it's not theirs, altho' they presume to take it, but the Lord's; yet this <hi>Priest (that thanks his God, that he doth not write for Bread)</hi> altho'
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46804:7"/> he pleads much for his <hi>Belly, Tithe Piggs</hi> and <hi>Geese,</hi> &amp;c. and pretends the like <hi>Provision (i. e.</hi> a settled <hi>Maintenance)</hi> hath been made for the <hi>Ministers</hi> of God in all Christian Nations—arising from the <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Possessions</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obser.</hi> This wants Proof, I desire to know of this Read Man, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Holland</hi> be a <hi>Christian Nation,</hi> and whether the <hi>Ministers</hi> there are paid from the <hi>Tythes</hi> of the Church, where none are demanded or paid.</p>
            <p>Again, If the <hi>People</hi> are the <hi>Church,</hi> and some of those People are common <hi>Cheats, Pick-pockets, Blasphemers, Impostors</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> as he calls the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ought these Ministers to be paid by such, or will they by <hi>force</hi> take <hi>Tythes</hi> from them that are not of their Church, nor Members of it; if he allows the <hi>Quakers</hi> are Members, then by his account, common <hi>Cheats, Pick-pockets, Blasphemers, Impostors,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> are <hi>Members</hi> of his <hi>Church;</hi> and if not, he would force them to pay that are not of the Church, from the <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessions</hi> of which they are to be paid, as he saith. And seeing he saith, They ought to be paid from the <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Possessions</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> then not from the <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Possessions</hi> of those that are not the <hi>Church.</hi> He saith also, That the denial or with-holding <hi>Tythe</hi> by the <hi>People,</hi> is <hi>Robbing</hi> of God: Indeed, some <hi>Jews</hi> were of old said so to do, when <hi>Tythes</hi> were <hi>Commanded</hi> of God; but <hi>Robbery</hi> was not in that day charged on the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that were not of the <hi>Jewish Church,</hi> neither ought it to be <hi>Charged</hi> now on the true <hi>Christians,</hi> that are acquitted from paying <hi>Tythes,</hi> either to the <hi>Jews,</hi> or such that call themselves <hi>Christians; for the</hi> Priesthood <hi>being Changed, there is of</hi> necessity <hi>a Change also of the</hi> Law <hi>that gave them;</hi> and the Law being <hi>Changed,</hi> and no New Law given by Christ, that requires the Payment of them, none are obliged to pay them to any of Christ's <hi>Ministers, For where there is no Law, there is no Transgression.</hi> Indeed the <hi>Apostle</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jesus Christ</hi> saith, <hi>The Lord hath ordained, that they which Preach the Gospel, should live by the Gospel;</hi> but he don't say, They must live by the <hi>Tythe Piggs, Geese</hi> and <hi>Corn,</hi> &amp;c. of those that do, not own them to be <hi>Ministers</hi> of the <hi>Gospel;</hi> and if this <hi>Priest</hi> would be accounted a <hi>Minister of the Gospel,</hi> let him prove himself so, seeing he saith, p. 7. <hi>Another Argument whereby the Quakers endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to Discredit the Parish Ministers with the People, they tell them, He is a Papist:</hi> This wants Proof, and he offers nothing but his confident say-so for it.</p>
            <p>However, seeing he hath started it, and calls the Quakers <hi>Knaves,</hi> and saith, <hi>Hereby they shew their Ignorance and Malice, by such causeless
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46804:7"/> and illiterate Aspersions.</hi> Let this Priest try if he can prove his <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> any other way than through the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and whether he hath any other <hi>Ordination</hi> or <hi>Call,</hi> but what was first received from <hi>Him,</hi> and the <hi>Popish Bishops;</hi> and then it may appear, whether he and his <hi>Brethren,</hi> or the <hi>Quakers,</hi> whom he saith none comes nearer the <hi>Papists,</hi> be most <hi>a-kin</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> whose <hi>Authority</hi> the <hi>Quakers</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly and altogether <hi>Reject</hi> and <hi>Deny,</hi> as meer <hi>Usurpation;</hi> and if he hath no other way to prove his <hi>Ordination</hi> or <hi>Call,</hi> may he not be justly accounted one of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>Emissaries,</hi> which I account <hi>signifies</hi> one <hi>Sent;</hi> and then, is not his <hi>Ordination, Call</hi> and <hi>Sending,</hi> by or from the <hi>Pope?</hi> And is he not an <hi>Emissary</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s? And may not I revert his Words upon him, and say, <hi>Never was Man more unlucky in an Objection?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He hath also another fling more at the poor <hi>Quakers</hi> and their <hi>Speakers,</hi> saying, p. 6. <q>There is not a <hi>Speaker</hi> of the Quakers, but what hath a better <hi>Maintenance,</hi> and picks up more than most <hi>Parish-Ministers.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And observe it where you will, you seldom or never meet with a Speaker amongst them, of any Name, but what is thought to be Rich, or else hath purchased a Visible Estate, of a considerable Value.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obser.</hi> This is a false Insinuation; If any are grown Rich, or got Estates, it hath not been by taking Peoples Goods by <hi>Force, Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> their <hi>Bodies,</hi> and <hi>Ruining</hi> their <hi>Families,</hi> that either did or did not Hear them: But it's to be feared; this <hi>Parson,</hi> nor his <hi>Brethren,</hi> will not follow the <hi>Quakers Example</hi> of Preaching freely, because they find their <hi>Preaching</hi> hath so little effect upon their <hi>Hearers,</hi> and their <hi>Love</hi> so small to them, considering how they behave themselves, that altho' they have a <hi>Law</hi> to <hi>Compel</hi> the paying their <hi>Maintenance,</hi> yet their Hearers don't willingly, but very <hi>unwillingly</hi> pay them, as he confesseth. Besides, if this Parson and his Brethren followed the Quakers Preachers Example, they must not only <hi>Preach freely,</hi> but use <hi>Care Diligence</hi> and <hi>Pains</hi> in their <hi>Trades</hi> and <hi>Imployments</hi> to get Money to <hi>provide</hi> for <hi>themselves</hi> and <hi>Families;</hi> and when God is pleased to bless their Endeavours and Industry in their lawful <hi>Imploys,</hi> they are truly thankful to him, and readily <hi>contribute</hi> according to their <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,</hi> towards the <hi>Relief</hi> and <hi>Assistance</hi> of them that stand in Need, and take Care that the <hi>Wives</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> of those, which such as he hath <hi>Ruined</hi> (and been <hi>Instrumental</hi> to make <hi>Widows</hi> and <hi>Fatherless)</hi> are provided for; and if because they are found in that Love, which is the Mark of the true <hi>Disciples of Christ,</hi> and by which, as he said, <hi>All Men should know they were his Disciples;</hi> this Priest, and such
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46804:8"/> angry ones (as he appears to be) are displeased, they cannot help it. Again, this <hi>Priest</hi> and his <hi>Brethren</hi> opening their <hi>Mouths,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying their <hi>Pens</hi> and the <hi>Press</hi> against the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and procure <hi>Curses</hi> and <hi>Excommunications</hi> for their not paying their <hi>Tythes</hi> or <hi>Easter Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konings,</hi> altho' it's well known to them, that well know the <hi>Quakers,</hi> that they are <hi>Quiet, Honest, Peaceable</hi> and <hi>Industrious People,</hi> that sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely desire to live in the Love and Fear of God; and such that so live, have, through his Assistance, demeaned themselves so, as to have a <hi>Conscience void of Offence</hi> to God, and towards all Men; and therefore hath the Lord <hi>frustrated</hi> the <hi>Designs</hi> of the <hi>Wicked,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained</hi> the <hi>Wrath</hi> of the <hi>Ungodly,</hi> altho' they have many times been like the <hi>Raging Waves</hi> of the Sea, casting forth <hi>Mire</hi> and <hi>Dirt, horrid Lyes</hi> and <hi>gross Slanders,</hi> against this Innocent <hi>People,</hi> yet the Lord that knows their Innocency, hath, and they trust will, as they abide in his Love, and dwell in his Fear, <hi>Deliver</hi> them out of all their <hi>Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> and <hi>Sweep away the Refuge of Lyes,</hi> and put the <hi>Lying Lips to Silence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Priest</hi> one while commends their <hi>Behaviour</hi> and <hi>Dress,</hi> and that it becomes the Pure in Heart; another while says, p. 8. <hi>They are fitted for Monkery, with all the tendency of Habit and Behaviour.</hi> What? Is that <hi>Dress</hi> which becomes the <hi>pure</hi> in Heart, <hi>fitted</hi> for <hi>Monkery?</hi> Hath he such a great <hi>Opinion</hi> for those, and is he so near of <hi>kin,</hi> as to commend their <hi>Habit</hi> and <hi>Behaviour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he hath not done with the <hi>Quakers</hi> yet, but saith, p. 8. <q>
                  <hi>And it's this Suspicion of their</hi> (i. e. Quakers) <hi>being Papists, that made many at Home Sorry, and Foreigners wonder at their having the Benefit of the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration;</hi> of which the <hi>Quakers</hi> are more unworthy, because they make another Use and Advantage of it, than the Government did, or does design they should.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obser.</hi> He pretends to be well acquainted with <hi>Foreigners,</hi> and says, they <hi>Wonder</hi> (because he Envies) at the <hi>Quakers</hi> having the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the <hi>Toleration</hi> (a thing he cannot endure) of which he saith, the <hi>Quakers</hi> are more unworthy; but who are they that are more worthy than the <hi>Quakers?</hi> Are they the <hi>Papists,</hi> because his Comparison or Writing is of the <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> saying, all Concluded and Expected they (i. e. <hi>Quakers)</hi> would (in King <hi>James</hi>'s Time) have declared and joyned with the <hi>Papists?</hi> But if all so <hi>Concluded</hi> and <hi>Expected,</hi> their <hi>Conclusion</hi> was wrong, and their <hi>Expectations</hi> frustrated, as is plainly manifested, as well as his <hi>Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion</hi> false. But what's the Use, and more Advantage, the <hi>Quakers</hi> make of the <hi>Toleration,</hi> than the <hi>Government</hi> did, or does design they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46804:8"/> should: This he tells not, because he knows of no more Ill <hi>Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> they make, than any other, and his <hi>Prejudice</hi> is evident enough against other <hi>Dissenters,</hi> whom he accounts <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Parties,</hi> against the <hi>Languishing-Church,</hi> as he saith, as well as the <hi>Quakers;</hi> only he pretends, p. 8. <hi>That the King and Parliament have been pleased to grant them</hi> (i. e. Quakers) <hi>a Toleration, and to take their bare Word in all Cases, when other Men are bound to Swear; whereby they would have People think, the Government have owned Quakerism to be the best Religion.</hi> The contrary of which appears, for if they did intend any more than a <hi>Toleration,</hi> they could have granted it; however, for that we are <hi>thankful,</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> the good <hi>Effects</hi> (notwithstanding the <hi>Anger</hi> of some <hi>Interested Men,</hi> whose <hi>Passion</hi> and <hi>Enmity</hi> is greater than their <hi>Wisdom</hi> and <hi>Conduct)</hi> will be a sufficient Encouragement to our Wise Legislators to continue it, that now we have Peace Abroad, we may injoy it at Home: But this Angry Priest hath not yet done using <hi>his poor Endeavours, according to his weak Ability,</hi> as he saith, to <hi>Incense</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> against the <hi>Quakers,</hi> by suggesting they have really <hi>forfeited</hi> all <hi>Pretences</hi> to it, and for Proof asserts two notorious <hi>Untruths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1st, <hi>That the Quakers deny the ever blessed and undivided Trinity:</hi> Of which he as <hi>confidently</hi> as <hi>falsly</hi> says, <hi>nothing is more certain than that they are against.</hi> When nothing is more true, than they do, and always did, own there are <hi>Three</hi> that bear Record in Heaven, the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> and these <hi>Three</hi> are One.</p>
            <p>Now, if to say <hi>Three,</hi> be not more Scriptural, than to say, <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and <hi>One,</hi> than <hi>Undivided,</hi> let the true Christians that <hi>love</hi> the <hi>Scripture,</hi> as we sincerely do, <hi>Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His 2<hi>d</hi> Untruth on this Head is expressed by him, p. 8. thus, <hi>They</hi> (i. e. Quakers) <hi>disown, both in their Writings and Preaching, the Divinity of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, and therefore it must needs follow, that they have no right to the Toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obser.</hi> What lying <hi>Stories</hi> this <hi>Hot, Angry,</hi> and <hi>Envious Priest</hi> vents, to render them such that have no right to the <hi>Toleration;</hi> those that are acquainted with their <hi>Books</hi> and <hi>Preaching,</hi> know that it's their <hi>Characteristick Principle,</hi> to assert, <hi>That the Word that was in the beginning with God, and was God, in which was Life; and the Life was the Light of Men; is the true Light, which lighteth every Man that cometh into the World,</hi> according to <hi>John</hi> 1. and that shews we own his <hi>Divinity,</hi> and ever did; and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> was made <hi>Flesh,</hi> and dwelt among us, according to <hi>John</hi> 1. 14.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:46804:9"/>
            <p> I could give account of more of his Untruths, but being many, have given a particular <hi>Catalogue</hi> of some of them: And I have been larger in my Answer to this Chapter than to the foregoing, or may be to the following, this being larger by far, than any of his others.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Meetings.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rem.</hi> Chap. 6. p. 12. <q>The Company meets, and the Speaker ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving staid some time for the Spirit, starts up—I shall not here make Sport with their <hi>Preaching—</hi>But I think we may safely expose that Dulness, Grunting and Groaning in the People, with those Postures and Grimaces, spitting in their Hands, and pulling off their Coats—However the Man, you may be sure, sheweth his best.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obser.</hi> How <hi>Scofflingly</hi> he Writes, and how <hi>Foully</hi> he Represents the <hi>Quakers</hi> here, as well as he hath <hi>falsly</hi> before; those that frequent their Meetings, do and may see their Behaviour, and hear their Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and can testifie; to whom I leave this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rem.</hi> Chap. 7. p. 13. This Man saith, <q>There cannot be a plainer Instance, and wherein the common People may better Judge for themselves, that the <hi>Quakers</hi> set their own Authority above the holy Scriptures, than their allowing the Women to Speak and Preach among them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obser.</hi> First his false Position or Suggestion of the Quakers setting their own Authority above the holy Scriptures is denyed, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing contrary to holy Scriptures do they hold; and his Instance is short of Proof, for the Apostle was not positively against any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Woman <hi>Blessing God's Name, Confessing</hi> to his <hi>Goodness,</hi> or <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or <hi>Prophecying</hi> in the Church, altho' he was for having them keep in Subjection, and not to Teach nor Usurp Authority over the Man, which the <hi>Quakers</hi> are against; but if any true <hi>Believing, Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Woman</hi> is opened, or moved by the Spirit of God, in the <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations</hi> of the Lord's People, to <hi>Pray</hi> or <hi>Prophesie,</hi> with her Head Covered, as the Apostle Adviseth, the <hi>Quakers</hi> dare not forbid it, and the <hi>Apostle</hi> Adviseth to it; and we are perswaded he intended what he expressed, that they should Learn in <hi>Silence,</hi> with all <hi>Sub-Subjection,</hi> and that a <hi>Woman should not be suffered to Teach nor Usurp Authority over the Man;</hi> for that would be no good <hi>Doctrine,</hi> for it would better become her to be in Silence, with all Subjection, and Learn of her Husband, as is advised before: But the Apostle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 3. saith, <hi>I intreat thee, true Yoak-fellow, help those Women which <hi>Laboured</hi> with me in the Gospel;</hi> so that there was Holy Sanctifyed <hi>Women</hi> that <hi>Laboured</hi> with him in the Gospel; and such that are <hi>Called</hi> and <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:46804:9"/> thereto, may now <hi>Labour</hi> in the <hi>Gospel,</hi> altho' he saith, either St. <hi>Paul</hi> or the <hi>Quakers</hi> are in the Wrong; it's his Mistake, and bare <hi>ipse dixit;</hi> and as he says, <hi>One would think there is no Body in his Wits. but would be on the Apostle's side;</hi> and truly the <hi>Quakers</hi> are, whatever he is, so much in their Wits, to be of the Apostle's Mind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rem.</hi> Chap. 8. p. 14. <q>Concerning the Fundamental Principle of the Quakers, or the Light within, and the mischievous Effects and Consequences of it—which fortifies them against all the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Adversaries.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obser.</hi> The <hi>Quakers</hi> indeed do profess and believe in <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> the <hi>Light within,</hi> who said, <hi>I am the Light of the World, and commanded to believe in the Light; who is that true Light that lighteth every One that cometh into the World; and is the Life of that Word that was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with God, and was God,</hi> and who <hi>commanded the Light to shine out of Darkness, and hath shined in our Hearts, to give the Light of the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Glory of God, in the Face of Jesus Christ, and through the Revelation of him, are they made partakers of that Knowledge which is Life Eternal;</hi> and <hi>Christ who is this Light,</hi> as this Priest acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he is, is not, nor cannot be, the Author of any <hi>mischievous Effects</hi> and <hi>Consequences,</hi> neither do <hi>dangerous Mistakes</hi> arise from the <hi>belief</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>Light within,</hi> as this Priest very <hi>Blindly</hi> and <hi>Blasphemously Asserts;</hi> neither doth <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>Light within</hi> destroy all <hi>Civil Dominion, Property</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as he saith, p. 16. but <hi>teacheth</hi> and <hi>strengthneth</hi> them to <hi>maintain</hi> and <hi>uphold</hi> it.</p>
               <p>He Asserts also in the same Page as followeth, <q>That another dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and blasphemous Consequence from the Opinion of the <hi>Light within,</hi> is, That the <hi>Quakers</hi> quite lay aside our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jesus Christ, thinking to be Saved without him.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obser.</hi> This is as notoriously false, as Positive and Blasphemous; for I Assert that it's through Faith in our <hi>Lord Jesus Christ that died for our Sins, and Obedience to him that Rose again for our Justification,</hi> and is in all true <hi>Believers,</hi> that the Quakers hope and expect to be saved by; and this Belief is no <hi>dangerous</hi> and <hi>blasphemous Consequence,</hi> as this Priest <hi>foully, blindly</hi> and <hi>blasphemously Asserts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet he again Asserts, in p. 16. <q>Nor will they <hi>(i. e. Quakers)</hi> acknowledge that there ever was in Earth, nor now is in Heaven, any other Christ, but what they have at present all within them; and so here is an end of the Divinity, Incarnation, Nativity, Passion, Satisfaction, Resurrection, Mediatorship, and Coming again to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obser.</hi> What a strange People this Priest would render the <hi>Quakers,</hi> through his outragious <hi>Envy,</hi> which he accounts commendable <hi>Zeal,</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:46804:10"/> altho' it's evident to be such <hi>Paul</hi> had, whilst <hi>Saul,</hi> by the very <hi>Rancor</hi> of it; I wish he doth it as <hi>ignorantly</hi> and <hi>blindly</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> did, and may come so to see it, as he did. And if this Priest, and all that think hardly of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> would be so considerate, as to lay aside all their Prejudices, and have so much Charity for them, as to believe what they have, and do frequently say and write, so far as it is according to Scripture, they would find their Mistake of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and that their <hi>Doctrines</hi> are not <hi>Erroneous, Heretical,</hi> or contrary to Scripture, however they are represented by some <hi>Interested</hi> and <hi>Prejudiced</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, that are found in the Spirit and Practice of those learned <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> and great <hi>Rabbies</hi> that called Christ <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> and that said, his <hi>Disciples were Drunk,</hi> or <hi>filled with new Wine, unlearned</hi> and <hi>accursed,</hi> and that esteemed the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> a <hi>Sect,</hi> which was almost <hi>every where</hi> spoken against, and <hi>persecuted</hi> them, as this Man would have the <hi>Quakers;</hi> altho' he pretends he is only for a <hi>tender Coertion,</hi> yet would he have them <hi>Innocently Suppressed,</hi> as in p. 29. but that <hi>tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> also is too much for those he is pleased to call <hi>Ring-leaders</hi> and <hi>Crafty Knaves.</hi> Howbeit I will here declare what they firmly believe, and in express Scripture-words, as much as I can:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It's that Jesus Christ, that was Born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and was sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to be the Son of</hi> Joseph, <hi>who about</hi> 1700 <hi>Years past appeared in the World, was manifest in the Flesh, wrought wonderful Miracles, preached excellent Doctrine, underwent a great Agony, Died for our Sins, Rose again for our Justification, and Ascended into Heaven, and is there the one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator between God and Man, the Man Christ Jesus; to whom all Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is committed, and Power given; and who declared himself the Light of the World, and was before the World began, and exhorted to believe in the Light, and is as truly now in the true Believers, as he was of old, yea, in all, except they are Reprobates; and the same Jesus Christ they firmly believe, shall himself Descend from Heaven, with a Shout, with the Voice of the Arch-Angel, and with the Trump of God, and the Dead in Christ shall rise first: And they own and believe there shall be a Resurrection both of the Just and Unjust.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore what this <hi>Priest</hi> hath asserted is <hi>false,</hi> for they believe there is not, nor ever was, any <hi>other Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> than him that they <hi>Profess</hi> and <hi>Believe</hi> in, that is the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> who before <hi>Pontius Pilate witnessed a good Confession, which in his times he shall shew, who is the Blessed and Only Potentate, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lord's, who only hath Immortality, dwelling in the Light which no Man can approach unto, whom no Man hath seen, nor can see: To whom be Honour and Power.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>This Priest notwithstanding goes on, in the same 16th page, falsly to Suggest or Charge, without bringing proof, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <q>And if the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:46804:10"/> have thus laid aside Jesus Christ himself, 'tis no wonder if they despise his Ordinances and Institutions; and we find by sad Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience they have—overturned the Priesthood, and preached down all outward Devotion and Decencies in Religion.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obser.</hi> This is false, for they have not laid aside Jesus Christ, nor do they despise any Ordinance or Institution of his; neither have they overturned that <hi>Priesthood</hi> which is <hi>changed,</hi> for that which took <hi>Tythes;</hi> neither have they preach'd <hi>down</hi> all <hi>outward Devotion</hi> and <hi>Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> altho' their Ministers do not wear <hi>Surplices,</hi> have not a <hi>Cushion</hi> to <hi>loll on,</hi> have not <hi>Organs</hi> and <hi>Singing-Boys,</hi> because they do not find they are any of Christ's Institutions nor Ordinances; but whatsoever by plain and express Scripture, and in plain and express Scripture-words, without the corrupt Meanings of those that do not pretend to the Guidance of Christ's Spirit, can be proved to be an <hi>Institution</hi> or <hi>Ordinance</hi> of Christ, which all his Followers are obliged to practice, they are for.</p>
               <p>P. 16, and 17. <q>This Light they <hi>(i. e. Quakers)</hi> say is Christ, and Christ is the Heir of all things, which gives them a Title to Inherit the Earth, and sets them above all Magistracy, Government and Laws, and so they are in a fair way to Invade the Estates and Goods of other Men, and will never want a pretence to justifie their <hi>Rapine.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obser.</hi> The Folly and Ridiculousness of what he saith, to Argue, Because <hi>Christ</hi> is Heir of all things, those that believe, and have a part in him, are in a fair way to <hi>Invade</hi> the <hi>Estates</hi> and <hi>Goods</hi> of other Men; What will he make of those that are true <hi>Christians,</hi> and of <hi>Christ</hi> that is their <hi>Leader</hi> and <hi>Teacher?</hi> Will he make him the Author of <hi>Sin,</hi> and the Justifier of <hi>Rapine?</hi> Oh Horrible! How will he like this Argument? He and his Brethren say, <hi>They believe in Christ, and Christ is Heir of all things:</hi> Therefore they are set above all <hi>Magistrates, Government</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> and are in a fair way to <hi>Invade</hi> the <hi>Estates</hi> and <hi>Goods</hi> of other Men, and will never want a pretence to Justifie their <hi>Rapine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed they have already began with the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and are in a fairer way to Ruin them under colour of Law, than the <hi>Quakers</hi> are, who only desire their, and all Men's Good, and Covet not what is theirs, but would be glad all those that <hi>Profess</hi> themselves <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> or <hi>Christians,</hi> were really guided in all things by <hi>Christ's Spirit,</hi> and walked according to the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> which many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess to be the only <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> that cannot prove their <hi>Faith</hi> thereby, and that do not Practice according to it, as the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable <hi>Pride,</hi> great <hi>Vanity,</hi> vicious <hi>Ways,</hi> ungodly <hi>Actions,</hi> execrable <hi>Oaths,</hi> grievous <hi>Imprecations,</hi> horrid <hi>Invocating of God to Damn their Souls,</hi> abundant <hi>Hatred,</hi> and bitter <hi>Envyings,</hi> in many, as too much thereof
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46804:11"/> is by this Priest evidently manifest: The Lord give him and them, if it be his Will, Repentance unto Life, before the day of Visitation be over.</p>
               <p>And altho' this Man wickedly saith, The Light within makes the <hi>Quakers Threaten, Curse</hi> and <hi>Damn</hi> all the World besides themselves: It's notoriously false, for <hi>Christ,</hi> who is the <hi>Light within</hi> all that are not <hi>Reprobates,</hi> fills the <hi>Quakers</hi> Hearts with Love and good Will to all, and makes them desirous that all Men, according to the Will of God, might be Saved and Redeemed by him that died for all Men, and that tasted Death for every Man; and therefore they Earnestly, and in great Love Exhort all to Believe in Christ, the <hi>true Light,</hi> that shews them their Sins, and tells them all that ever they did; and to receive his Spirit, that convinceth them of their Sins, and reproves them for their evil Deeds, and to learn of his Grace, that they may be taught to deny all <hi>Ungodliness,</hi> the Cause of God's Wrath, and to learn of his Grace, to live <hi>Soberly</hi> and <hi>Righteously,</hi> that they may enjoy Peace, and Dye in God's Favour, and be Blessed for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. p. 18. <q>I have not misrepresented them in the least here, for nothing hath been charged to their Score, but what is naturally deducible from their great Principle, the <hi>Light within.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obser.</hi> The horrible <hi>Confidence</hi> and <hi>Falshood</hi> of this Man is great, thus to Assert; for either he is ignorant of the <hi>Quakers Principle,</hi> or he is very wicked in what he hath said; for the <hi>Quakers</hi> never meant nor intended any thing thereby, but Christ the Word of God, <hi>of which the Righteousness</hi> (p. 16. and he acknowledgeth as much) <hi>of Faith speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on this wise, Say not in thine Heart, Who shall Ascend into Heaven (that is, to bring Christ down from above) and that Word is nigh thee</hi> (i. e. every Man) <hi>even in thy Mouth and in thy Heart,</hi> and is that Word of Faith which the Apostles preached (and the Quakers now Preach) yet this blind Priest saith, p. 19. <hi>The Light within is the Foundation and Corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, upon which the Quakers lay all the stress and weight of Babel.</hi> And yet p. 14. he grants what they mean by the <hi>Light within,</hi> viz. <hi>An Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Inspiration of the Holy Ghost, or Revelation sent from God.</hi> Now can any Body believe this Man hath not misrepresented the <hi>Quakers in the least; and that nothing hath been charged to their Score, but what is naturally deducible from their great Principle:</hi> Is it naturally deducible from the Quakers owning Christ, the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Light within,</hi> or an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiration</hi> from the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> &amp;c. That <hi>Christ,</hi> and the <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Light within, Is the Foundation and Corner of Babel?</hi> And doth, from their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief hereof; these <hi>dangerous</hi> and <hi>blasphemous Consequences</hi> follow, which he hath Asserted, <hi>viz. That they lay aside our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, and think to be Saved without him; and to deny or make an end of the Divinity, Incarnation, Nativity, Passion, Satisfaction and Resurrection,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46804:11"/> Mediatorship and Coming again, of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, without th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>se</hi> they believe and know him to be within them; Oh! How Horrib<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and Abominable are these things? And what a height of <hi>Impudence,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deep <hi>Hypocrisie,</hi> and great <hi>Darkness,</hi> is this Man In! Can any believe him to be a Minister of Christ, that thus writes? Surely nay; and many other undue and unconsequential <hi>Consequences</hi> he hath <hi>foully</hi> asserted, and <hi>falsly</hi> drawn, as I have shewn before, from the <hi>Quakers</hi> owning <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>Light within.</hi> He saith, They lay the <hi>stress</hi> of a <hi>Babel</hi> upon it: But let him know, It's the Lord that is strong, in whom the Quakers believe; he that judgeth <hi>Babylon</hi> and her <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,</hi> and causeth them to Weep and Mourn, for no Man buyeth her <hi>Merchandize</hi> any more; I say, It's he that doth this, in whom the <hi>Quakers</hi> believe, and therefore is not the <hi>Corner and Foundation-stone of</hi> Babylon, as this Priest falsly saith: But he hath not done yet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. p. 19. The Title is, <hi>The Grand Impostor of the Light within.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obs.</hi> Altho' he most wickedly calls the <hi>Light within. The grand Impostor,</hi> yet p. 18. he speaketh of the Quakers preaching up the <hi>Word,</hi> and the <hi>Christ of God—</hi>the <hi>Light within;</hi> and is the <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Christ of God,</hi> and <hi>Light within,</hi> an <hi>Impostor?</hi> Is not this most notorious <hi>Blasphemy,</hi> which would <hi>Astonish</hi> a sober <hi>Christian Man</hi> to hear? And yet this Man proceeds, and saith, p. 19. <hi>By the Light within, I bave shewed you, That the Quakers mean an Immediate Revelation from God:</hi> Do they so? And is an <hi>Immediate Revelation</hi> from God, the <hi>grand Impostor?</hi> It may well be said, <hi>The way of the Wicked is Darkness, and they know not at what they stumble;</hi> and that it's <hi>they that do Evil, hate the Light.</hi> And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding this Man hath said of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> p. 15. <hi>The Quakers will not, in their Controversies with others, be judged by the Holy Scriptures:</hi> They do sincerely declare. They desire no <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Principle</hi> they hold, should be by any received, but what's agreeable to <hi>holy Scripture,</hi> or no ways contradictory thereto; and they desire often, as I do of this Priest, <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>express</hi> Scripture-proof for what he saith and writes; and that he would give <hi>plain</hi> Scripture for what he saith in this Chap. p. 19. viz. <hi>How no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more certain, than that Immediate Revelation has ceased long ago, both as to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs and Effects of it: And that there can be no such thing. That the Gospel, which the Apostles preached, God intended should be a Rule of Faith, and Standard of Religion to all Ages of the World: And that there is no other way of coming to the knowledge of God's Will, but by the holy Scriptures: And that the occasion of Immediate Inspiration is ceased, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy was sealed and closed up: And that the Light within is nothing but a meer Cheat;</hi> with much more that he hath said of the <hi>Light within;</hi> let the <hi>Quakers</hi> have <hi>plain</hi> Scripture for these things.</p>
               <p>This Priest is also much displeased at the <hi>Preachers</hi> or <hi>Speakers</hi> among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and says, p. 22. <hi>The Quakers have nothing of Divinity or Learning in them; nor do I know how it should be otherwise, for it's very unlikely, that a Man that hath served seven Years to a sorry Trade, and after all, not Master of it, should on a sudden, and in few days, be fit for a Pulpit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obs.</hi> Doth this Priest think it unlikely for a Man to be fit for a Pulpit, without ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving seven Years to get the knack of talking by Notes, for an hour in a Pulpit, which if he can't attain to, he may repeat some old Sermon by Roat, which he may buy for two Pence, that may serve: But I would have him consider, whether the holy Apostles were not as <hi>Illiterate,</hi> as some <hi>Preachers</hi> amongst the <hi>Quakers;</hi> and yet more were <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted</hi> to God, and turned from the Evil of their Ways, at one Sermon of their <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:46804:12"/> than, I am perswaded, there have been ever since, by all the <hi>Man-made-Ministers</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> or else-where, that did not Minister in the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Quakers</hi> matter not, if they are by the <hi>Rabbies</hi> of our <hi>Age</hi> called, as the <hi>Apostles</hi> were in their Day, <hi>Illiterate</hi> and <hi>Ʋnlearned</hi> Men, so long as they find the <hi>Lord</hi> with them, and his <hi>Presence</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> attending their Ministry: And so I shall leave this Chapter, and pass by his idle Story of <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> and scoffs at the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiration,</hi> and proceed to his 11th Chap.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. p. 24. He falsly saith, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <q>We may therefore safely conclude, they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit the Holy Ghost, to his great Scandal and Vexation; for hereby they Charge and Father upon him, all their <hi>(i. e.</hi> Quakers) Mistakes, Fooleries, Infirmities, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies, Villanies, and knavish Tricks; making him a Principal with them all the while, which is an horrible Blasphemy, and must needs do great Dishonour and Despite to the Spirit of Grace.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obs.</hi> This is notoriously false: and if he and his Brethren conclude, The <hi>Quakers</hi> counterfeit the holy Ghost, and do as above-said, they utterly deny it; howbeit that wicked <hi>Conclusion</hi> is no proof, neither doth it appear, or is likely, that those who use a constant Care to keep from vain <hi>Oaths,</hi> and idle <hi>Expressions,</hi> as this Priest saith the Quakers do, and are <hi>so far from Pride, and the Flattery of the World, that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver give nor take the common Civilities of the Age, or Country, and whose Intentions Men may judge of, by their outside, whose Dress is Mean and Humble, such as becomes the Pure in Heart, which is justly commendable;</hi> I say, It is not likely that that these Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers are Guilty of such <hi>Heresies, Villanies, knavish Tricks, and horrible Blasphemy, and do great Dishonour and Despite to the Spirit of Grace:</hi> For if they were found in such Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Villany and Blasphemy, surely any might conclude, They would not be Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, but Condemnable: But this Priest, like some other of his Hot, Angry Brethren, are endeavouring to render, by Lyes and Slanders, the Quakers <hi>Odious</hi> and <hi>Obnoxious,</hi> and are calling them <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Blasphemers,</hi> and charging them to be guilty of <hi>Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> and <hi>knavish Tricks,</hi> that they might encite the <hi>Populacy</hi> against them, and prevail with some, whom they can Ride, and will take things upon Trust from them, to cry out against the <hi>Quakers,</hi> to stir up <hi>Persecution,</hi> the thing they want; <hi>Jails, Fines</hi> and <hi>Ruin,</hi> is what they want to have exercis'd upon the <hi>Quakers:</hi> And it's greatly to be feared, That some of those Men, that are so <hi>fierce</hi> in this Work, that wants to have them <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed,</hi> and <hi>Coertion exercised against the Quakers,</hi> and are comparing them to <hi>Papists;</hi> are notwithstanding secretly influenced by some <hi>Popish Emissaries</hi> that envy the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Happiness</hi> that the <hi>Protestants</hi> at present Enjoy, and would frustrate the good Design of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> in giving the <hi>Toleration,</hi> which was for the <hi>Ʋniting</hi> his <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Subjects</hi> in <hi>Interest and Affection;</hi> that by dividing them, in <hi>Affection,</hi> they might weaken them in their <hi>Interest;</hi> and if they could prevail so to effect their Design, they might Rejoyce that they had prevailed with the <hi>Church of England,</hi> to imitate the <hi>Papists</hi> in <hi>Persecution,</hi> one of their worst <hi>Practices,</hi> and that had got her again into that, which more than once, to excuse themselves of, they said, Was done by a <hi>Popish Interest;</hi> and its well known, that some of those <hi>Tools,</hi> which were <hi>countenanced</hi> by the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in King <hi>Charles</hi>'s time, were known <hi>Papists,</hi> altho' so greatly encouraged.</p>
               <p>And those <hi>Priests</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that are so <hi>Hot</hi> and <hi>Fierce</hi> now for <hi>Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> and <hi>Coertion,</hi> can see little farther than their Noses, that esteem this their <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest,</hi> or that think this will <hi>Convince</hi> any, that they are the <hi>Ministers</hi> of him, that said, concerning the <hi>Wheat</hi> and <hi>Tares, Let both grow together;</hi> for altho' an <hi>Enemy Sowed</hi> the <hi>Tares, yet the Houshoulder,</hi> when he was <hi>Informed</hi> thereof, by his <hi>Servants,</hi> forbid <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of them, lest the Wheat were rooted up with them.</hi> And it's hoped the Wisdom of the present <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> will be such, as to follow this Advice, although these <hi>Priests</hi> may esteem themselves like those that asked leave to <hi>Call or Command for Fire to come down from Heaven,</hi> yet let them remember that Christ rebuked them, and said, <hi>They knew not what manner of Spirit they were of.</hi> So this Priest not knowing what Spirit
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46804:12"/> he is of, or not <hi>acting</hi> according to what he <hi>professeth</hi> himself, goes on in his evil Work, as will yet appear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. p. 25. This Chapter is about <hi>Swearing,</hi> wherein he would have us not take the Text in the plain and express Scripture terms, but his Exposition or Addition, for where it is said, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> and where it is said, <hi>Swear not by any Oath;</hi> he contradicts the Texts, and says, We may Swear sometimes; and where it's said, <hi>Swear not by any Oath,</hi> he says, We may Swear by some <hi>Oath;</hi> and for proof he saith, God Commanded his People to <hi>Swear</hi> under the <hi>Law,</hi> before Christ, that is the End of the Law, and that recited the Law, when he gave this <hi>Command,</hi> and forbid <hi>all Swearing;</hi> he told them what was commanded in the Old Law, which never allowed the People to Swear in their common Communication; but Christ was minded, it appears, to carry it <hi>farther,</hi> therefore after he had reminded them of what was commanded, <hi>viz. That thou shalt not forswear thy self, but shalt perform unto the Lord thine Oath</hi> (mind, perform thy Oath, that could not be a vain and common Oath) for such are many times better broke than kept; but such Oath, that under the old Law was allowed, <hi>But I say unto you, Swear not at all;</hi> now who must the Quakers believe, he that never spake a-miss, that is, that great <hi>Prophet,</hi> that in all things they ought to hear, or this Priest, whose Spirit and Works declare he is one of those <hi>idle Shepherds, that feeds himself, and not the Flock?</hi> And is it not apparent, that this Priest's Voice is the Voice of the Stranger, because he speaks contrary to Christ, and contrary to his Apostles; For the 1st says, <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> The 2d says, <hi>Swear not by any Oath.</hi> This Priest says, <hi>We ought to Swear,</hi> and we must <hi>Swear by some Oath;</hi> nay, he complains of the Quakers, and says, They hold it not lawful or safe to <hi>Swear</hi> at all, altho' the Magistrate Command; What would he have the Magistrates Command obeyed, and not Christ's? Surely here the Parson is besides his Cushion, but he hath still one Story to tell, which if he might be believed, is mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact (but I desire none may believe the latter part of it, till the Fact is proved, for its pity the Quakers should have <hi>Abbington-</hi>Law) however he saith, 'Tis matter of Fact, that never were Men so abused, as the Quakers, by the <hi>Popish Priests;</hi> he might have added, and by me and some of my Brethren: Nor as we by the Quakers (this wants proof) under the plausible pretence of the unlawfulness of Swearing—and <hi>it is put in the Mouths of the Quakers to preach it up:</hi> Oh! strange, Would the <hi>Quakers</hi> be so good conditioned to suffer this to be put in their Mouths, by them that abuse them: Oh! this poor Priest fumbles and makes poor work of it. If he could prove that <hi>Papists put it first in the Quakers Mouths;</hi> let him prove who these cunning <hi>Papists</hi> and abused Quakers were, and where this strange Fact was done, and who were the Witnesses of it; then he may expect some Reward, but till then he may rest satisfied, that he hath exposed his Folly, and shewed his Enmity, and yet must stand charged with <hi>Lying Forgery,</hi> and being a <hi>False Accuser,</hi> till he can bring <hi>sufficient Evidence</hi> to prove what he hath writ and published to the World is true; so I may conclude with his own words, <hi>Never were Men so abused as the Quakers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am now come to his Conclusion, and wherein he vents his Malice, and shews his Shapes, and calls the Quakers, <hi>Wolves in Sheeps Cloathing, and Saints with Cloven-feet—They have renounced Christianity; they have wholly laid aside our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ; They have despised the holy Scriptures; Their Design's utterly inconsistent with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent State. We are like to suffer by them in our civil Interest without Regard or Obligation to Worldly Rulers,</hi> and suggests <hi>we have reason to fear and expect Revolutions effected in States and Kingdoms by them—most capable and inclinable to disturb our Peace The Quakers have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the fundamental Principle of Christianity, and become Heretical, and are at an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilable Distance; and should they succeed, there'll be no Quarter, neither for Church nor State, for no Religion will be Tolerated, no Laws admitted but their own; therefore let us Consult our own Security, by Restraining them, seeing the</hi> Quakers <hi>are such Blasphemers, and Heretical Persons;</hi> and he is <hi>for</hi> Coertion, <hi>and to have them</hi> Suppressed; <hi>but the Ring-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> he saith, <hi>are not worthy of such</hi> Compassion: <hi>Something therefore must be done, not put
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46804:13"/> off to some future Care; and all that he is afraid of, he hath not set them in such Colours as those Blasphemers and Impostors,</hi> as he calls the Quakers, <hi>deserve;</hi> and he <hi>wishes he were able to say something that would be Prevalent and Perswasive,</hi> to what? to Persecution, Oh! how Earnest and Endustrious is this <hi>Priest</hi> to stir up <hi>Persecution</hi> against the poor <hi>Quakers? 1st,</hi> By rendring them <hi>Hereticks, Wolves or Cloven-foot Saints, Impostors,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Renouncers of Christianity, layers aside of Christ, despisers of the holy Scriptures, denyers of the Trinity, inconsistent with the State, without regard to worldly Rulers,</hi> most <hi>capable and inclinable to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturb our Peace.</hi> 2d. <hi>By calling to have them Restrained, Coertion exercised against them;</hi> Would they have Fire and Faggot, Hanging, Imprisonment, Confiscation of Goods, or what Cruelties would they have infflicted on them, that this <hi>Priest,</hi> and some of his <hi>hot, angry Brethren,</hi> are so fierce? and what is the Cause? Is it that the <hi>Quakers</hi> are <hi>Immoral</hi> in their <hi>Lives,</hi> or have been <hi>Ʋnpeaceable</hi> in their <hi>Conversations,</hi> under any of the various Governments in which they have lived, since they were a People? Or are they <hi>unchristian</hi> in <hi>Doctrine?</hi> Or can it be proved, altho' falsly suggested, that they are <hi>Despisers</hi> of the <hi>holy Scriptures,</hi> or holders of <hi>any Doctrine</hi> contrary thereto, or deniers of <hi>Christ?</hi> Surely nay; neither are the Quakers <hi>Robbers</hi> of <hi>Churches,</hi> or <hi>Blasphemers,</hi> any more than <hi>Paul,</hi> as the Town-Clark of <hi>Ephesus</hi> said to the Tumult raised by <hi>Demetrius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And altho' the Priest may Incense the People against the <hi>Quakers,</hi> saying, <hi>Sirs, ye know by this Craft we have our Wealth;</hi> and these Quakers have <hi>perswaded and turned away much People;</hi> but said the <hi>Town Clark to the People, Ye ought to be Quiet</hi> (and so ought these Priests) and do nothing rashly, for these <hi>Quakers</hi> are neither <hi>Robbers</hi> of <hi>Churches,</hi> nor yet <hi>Blasphemers;</hi> and if this Priest, or his Brethren, have ought against the <hi>Quakers,</hi> they know, as the <hi>Town-Clark</hi> said to the <hi>Tumult, The Law is open;</hi> and indeed many of these angry Priests have thereby made great <hi>Havock</hi> and <hi>Spoil</hi> of Goods, and brought <hi>Ruin</hi> and <hi>Imprisonment</hi> upon many <hi>Quakers,</hi> for very small matters, rendring themselves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by more <hi>Cruel</hi> and <hi>Ʋnmerciful,</hi> than any other<hi>-Trades-men</hi> do for any just Debt, of so small Sums, altho' their <hi>Debtors</hi> have had a Valuable Consideration for what is demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and notwithstanding this severe Dealing, these Men are not Content, but would have <hi>new Laws</hi> made to gratifie their Revenge, and to Ruin all the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by their <hi>Out-cries</hi> and <hi>Clamours,</hi> which is not the way to prove themselves to be in the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Ministers,</hi> or to convince the <hi>Quakers</hi> they are such, when their <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Fruits</hi> declare the contrary: I would therefore <hi>Advise</hi> this <hi>Parson, to study to be Quiet, and to follow Peace with all Men, and Holiness, without which none shall see the Lord;</hi> and if he must be <hi>provoking,</hi> let it not be to <hi>Persecution,</hi> but <hi>Love and good Works; and let all Bitterness, Wrath, Anger, Clamour and Evil-speaking, be put away, with all Malice, and let him put on Bowels of Mercy, Goodness, Humbleness of Mind, Meekness, Long-suffering, and let him remember, If any Man have a Quarrel against any, let him forgive, as Christ forgave: And whatsoever things are true, honest, just, pure, lovely, of good report; if there be any virtue, if there he any praise, let him think on these things,</hi> and do them, and no more be found marring of <hi>Paper</hi> and imploying the <hi>Press</hi> with his <hi>false, bitter, angry Clamour,</hi> and <hi>Evil speaking,</hi> against a <hi>People</hi> that are <hi>quiet</hi> in the Land, of sober <hi>Lives,</hi> of christian <hi>Conversations,</hi> and are just and honest in their <hi>Dealings,</hi> are true, honest, just, and of good <hi>Report, that render to</hi> Caesar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caesar<hi>'s, and to</hi> God, <hi>the things that are</hi> God<hi>'s, and to all Men their Dues;</hi> altho' they can't for Conscience sake pay <hi>Tythes,</hi> to such who account themselves <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and have never proved that Christ gave any Command to his Disciples, to <hi>pay them</hi> to his <hi>Ministers,</hi> nor his <hi>Ministers</hi> to <hi>receive them,</hi> there being no such <hi>Legacy</hi> given by the <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stator</hi> of the New Testament, in all his <hi>Testament:</hi> And if he believe the Scriptures to be the only <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> he should walk according to it, and not contrary; and this would abundantly more become him, considering he saith, <hi>He is a Priest,</hi> than <hi>belying, falsly accusing, and misrepresenting the Quakers,</hi> and their <hi>Principles,</hi> and therefore as the Angel said, when discoursing with the Devil, about the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Moses,</hi> I shall say to him, <hi>The Lord Rebuke thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <byline>By one that is called a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
               </byline>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:46804:13"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>